<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Technical Musing of a Mummy</title>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com" />
<updated>2016-02-05T19:45:51+00:00</updated>
<id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/</id>
<author>
  <name>Heather Campbell</name>
  <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com/</uri>
  <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: The Phoenix Project]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/review-the-phoenix-project/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/review-the-phoenix-project</id>
  <published>2016-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/The-Phoenix-Project-Helping-Business-ebook/dp/B00AZRBLHO&quot;&gt;Phoenix project&lt;/a&gt; is a fictitious novel which follows Bill in his new role as VP of IT operations at Parts Unlimited. Mentored by Erik, a potential board member, Bill and his colleagues turn around a department which is firefighting, missing deadlines and misaligning with the organisation’s objectives. They create an IT department which can respond rapidly to changing markets and deliver IT systems which help the company meet their targets and gain competitive advantage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-thoughts&quot;&gt;My Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The style of the book makes it a quick and easily read introduction to devops. It delivers a plethora of information (based on the length of my notes) on ways you can improve how your team, department and company operate in an easily digestible fashion. It could be argued that change and improvement come too easily in the book but that didn’t bother me. The point of the book is to distil information in an easy to absorb manner not win a literary book award.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the improvements were things I was already aware of and which I see implemented in the projects I work on but it is still a useful reminder. The thing that really stuck with me is to not be a bystander but to be someone who actively challenges the norm and looks for ways to improve things. Don’t be a yes woman. Be someone willing to take a risk and innovate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;takeaways&quot;&gt;Takeaways&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are some of my takeaways&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Co-ordination and communication across teams, roles and departments is key especially during times of pressure.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Regular outages mean you are reactive and take up resource and time meant to be spent on planned work. Need to understand why they are happening and put measures in place to stop them happening.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Know your constraints including people and have plans in place for how to reduce dependency on them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Make sure you exploit your constraint  so it is never waiting on anything. Focus on top priority work and set tempo of work according to constraints&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Avoid knowledge silos. Make sure the heroes in your company share knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Not throwing code over the wall. Developers shouldn’t consider their code successful until it is deployed to live and working as expected. Need to work with ops to supply them the knowledge required to achieve this.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It is not enough to have a process in place. It must be light weight enough for people to follow it&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importance of testing including non-functional testing e.g. performance, capacity testing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Design code for operations. Non-functionals should be built in early and not an after thought.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Integrate security into day to day work not an afterthought&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Controlled release of features and change so you know exactly what code/features/configuration exist in an environment e.g. source control of code including build configuration, automated deployment, reproducible environments&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importance of having monitoring and health checks in place to warn of issues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Work In Progress is a silent killer&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Theory of constraints: improvements made anywhere beyond bottleneck are illusion. Identify your bottleneck and make improvements there to stop it being a bottleneck … then find the next bottleneck&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Value in visualizing work to be done and flow through system  e.g. kanban board&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Outcomes are key. Focus on what is important to business. Avoid needless work. Question need to do work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a culture which allows for blameless post-mortems so you can get down to the real root cause of issues.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importance of paying down technical debt. Like financial debt, the compounding interest costs grow over time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need ability to say no and not blindly say yes&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Improving daily work is even more important than doing it&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Need metrics to make informed decision&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Importance of making time for retrospectives&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Know end goals and align with them. Linking individual objectives with team, department and organisational objectives. E.g. a department’s goals may be reliant on delivery by IT so there is a risk if IT does not deliver. Integrate IT into performance measures.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Talk to business owners, understand processes and goals, your role in achieving them, concerns and risks&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reduce cycle times e.g. move to 2 week sprints. Get feature to market quickly to test assumptions and get feedback from customers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Guard assets. Protect them from distractions.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Identify common processes/steps, standardize and automate them&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Encourage experimentation, innovation and risk taking. Make it ok to fail.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/review-the-phoenix-project/&quot;&gt;Review: The Phoenix Project&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on February 04, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading Challenge]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/reading-challenge/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/reading-challenge</id>
  <published>2016-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-02-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hard to believe I’m nearly 2 months into maternity leave. The days are flying in. Marc arrived on the 15th December and I’m now well outnumbered 3 boys to 1 girl.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In these early days a large amount of my time is spent feeding Marc especially as I feed him on demand. Having already completed all six seasons of Private Practice, a couple of seasons of Girls and started rewatching Greys Anatomy I thought maybe it was time to find something outside of boxsets to entertain me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feeding Marc gives me lots of opportunity to sit, not to mention the time spent trapped under him while he sleeps (his sensors for when he is being put down are as good as Luke’s. Cue eyes open and tears) so I’m finally tackling my backlog of books. I came across this article on twitter &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/how-even-the-busiest-entrepreneur-can-read-100-books-a-year.html&quot;&gt;reading 100 books in a year&lt;/a&gt; and I’m following some of the tips in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;buy-books-in-advance&quot;&gt;Buy books in advance&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not an issue. As mentioned previously I’ve a backlog of books to get through. I’m easily seduced by an offer and tend to buy multiple books at a time. I’ve also got a long wishlist of books I want to read so reading material is not a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;always-be-reading&quot;&gt;Always be reading&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sorted now that I’m being kept in one place by my little son.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;read-what-you-like&quot;&gt;Read what you like&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve a load of software books I want to read as well as some aimed at the softer side of my job. I need to find some good fiction to put into the mix. I used to read fiction and autobiographies all the time but, post children, magazines have taken over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tracking-my-reading&quot;&gt;Tracking my Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found out about the goodreads reading challenge tracker on twitter and decided to give it a whirl. It’ll help me keep momentum. I’ve set an achievable target of 12 books, one for each month (100 was a bit ambitious for me!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/images/reading/readingchallenge.png&quot; alt=&quot;Reading Challenge&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past week I’ve discovered ebooks work best. I’ve mastered the art of feeding Marc while reading my ebook and taking notes on my phone using Evernote. In fact I’ve even taken it to the next level, feeding, expressing and reading at once. Multitasking to the max.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before  having Marc I preferred paper books for reading but trying to hold a paper book and feed is just too much of a fiddle. Being able to flick between reading and taking notes on the same device is so much simpler. I’ve completed my January book, The Phoenix Project, and moved onto Lean UX so going well so far.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/reading/reading-challenge/&quot;&gt;Reading Challenge&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on February 02, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developer Tea]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/developer-tea/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/developer-tea</id>
  <published>2016-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2016-01-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past week I’ve started listening to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developertea.com&quot;&gt;Developer Tea&lt;/a&gt; podcast. None of the episodes are long with each one averaging less than 20 mins. A lot of the podcasts I enjoy are an hour or more in length so it is a nice addition to have one which is shorter for when I want a quick burst of inspiration. Episodes are recorded regularly for example in the past week alone there have been three episodes, &lt;em&gt;Learning on the Job&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Comparison Conundrums&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Feature’s You Don’t Need&lt;/em&gt;. Each episode is well structured, often providing actionable advice to help you make positive changes. Definitely worth checking out.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/developer-tea/&quot;&gt;Developer Tea&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on January 21, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Functional Programming with Java]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/technologies/functional-programming-with-java/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/technologies/functional-programming-with-java</id>
  <published>2015-10-22T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-22T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just completed &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jessitron&quot;&gt;Jessica Kerr’s&lt;/a&gt; Pluralsight course &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pluralsight.com/courses/java-functional-programming&quot;&gt;Functional Programming with Java&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not the first time I’ve played about with Java 8 and its functional features or functional programming in general. I still found the course useful especially as I applied what it covered to a project I worked on several years ago which was purely Object Orientated. This gave me a chance to put it in to practice and get a feel of the benefits this additional functionality provided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;BTW if you haven’t read/watched anything created by Jessica before I really recommend that you should check out her &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.jessitron.com&quot;&gt;blog&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jessitron&quot;&gt;twitter feed&lt;/a&gt;. The quality of what she produces was one of the things which attracted me to the course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-easy-to-read-code&quot;&gt;Create easy to read code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever had to support or enhance someone elses code you’ll appreciate the importance of creating code which is easy to follow. In an ideal world code should be &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-documenting&quot;&gt;self-documenting&lt;/a&gt;. Two of the big benefits I found when rewriting the project using functional programming was it really focuses you on breaking the code down into small reusable functions and, where appropriate, separating out the side effects from the core computation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the ability to chain functions together allows you to create code that reads much more like the business requirements it is trying to satisfy. Functions can be passed as parameters and used as return values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;code-highlight-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;code-highlight-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-title&quot;&gt;prescription.java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5a0e4d916fcf5ccd44ce&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;code-highlight-pre&quot;&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Predicate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAYABLE&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getStatus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Payable&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* cost of prescription is sum of total cost of payable items on &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;5&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;   the prescription */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;6&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;totalCostOfPrescription&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;        
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;7&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PAYABLE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;8&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;totalCost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;9&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;Double:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;10&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;orElse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can go one step further, a reasonable assumption is that we’ll want to filter prescription items on more than one criteria so lets create a common filter function that accepts a predicate, a statement that returns true or false depending on the value passed in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;code-highlight-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;code-highlight-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-title&quot;&gt;prescription2.java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5a0e4d916fcf5ccd44ce&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;code-highlight-pre&quot;&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Predicate&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PAYABLE&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                          &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getStatus&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Payable&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;private&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;prescriptionItemStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;5&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getPrescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;6&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;7&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;8&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;filterPrescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;9&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                   &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Predicate&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filterCriteria&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;10&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;11&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;prescriptionItemStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;filterCriteria&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;12&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;13&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;14&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;getPayablePrescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;15&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;16&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;filterPrescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;PrescriptionItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;PAYABLE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;17&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;18&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;19&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;/* cost of prescription is sum of total cost of payable items on &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;20&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;cm&quot;&gt;   the prescription */&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;21&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;totalCostOfPrescription&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;getPayablePrescriptionItems&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;22&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;map&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;totalCost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;23&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;reduce&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;Double:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;sum&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;24&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                                 &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;orElse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mf&quot;&gt;0.00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example we’re filtering, mapping and reducing each item. You might think to look at it we’re iterating through and filtering each item, then iterating again and mapping and then iterating again and reducing. Infact it is much more efficient than that. There is only one iteration round the prescription items which the functions being called on each item in turn. I recommend checking out the ‘One Trip Through’ and ‘Lazy Streams’ sections of the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pluralsight.com/courses/java-functional-programming&quot;&gt;Course&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another bonus to the code above is we’re being &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declarative_programming&quot;&gt;declarative&lt;/a&gt;. We’re writing code that represents the business logic rather than the control flow to carry it out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;avoid-duplication-and-magic&quot;&gt;Avoid duplication and magic&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can’t take credit for the following example as it is lifted from Jessica’s course. The function can be used to time a piece of code. It wraps the code which is passed in using the Supplier. To avoid tying ourselves to a particular means of displaying the code we pass in the output method using Consumer. In the example below I’m using System.out but in real life it is more likely to be your logging framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;code-highlight-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;code-highlight-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-title&quot;&gt;timeOperation.java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5a0e4d916fcf5ccd44ce&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;code-highlight-pre&quot;&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;timeOperation&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;operationName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Consumer&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Supplier&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Date&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;before&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;Date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;code&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;5&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;final&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Long&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;Date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;before&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getTime&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;6&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;output&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;accept&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;operationName&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; took &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;duration&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot; milliseconds&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;7&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;result&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;8&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;9&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;10&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Timer&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;timeOperation&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;CalculatePrescriptionCost&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;11&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                     &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;12&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;                     &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;calculatePrescriptionCost&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prescription&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This follows the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Separation_of_concerns&quot;&gt;separation of concerns&lt;/a&gt; design principle. We’re not mixing our timing code with our calculation logic. It is reusable so we’re keeping our code &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Don%27t_repeat_yourself&quot;&gt;DRY&lt;/a&gt;. This can be achieved other ways currently e.g. via annotations but this is much more explicit with the implementation and the link less hidden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simplication-of-making-operations-parallel&quot;&gt;Simplication of making operations parallel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we’re gathering stats on the treatment carried out by a particular contractor. This could be very CPU intensive and we might want to parallelize it. You can see in the example below it is as simple as adding parallel() after the stream, our business logic stays the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;code-highlight-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;code-highlight-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-title&quot;&gt;parallalContractorTreatmentStats.java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5a0e4d916fcf5ccd44ce&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;code-highlight-pre&quot;&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// get stats for total cost of treatment carrier out by each contractor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DoubleSummaryStatistics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;         &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatmentStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;collect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;5&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;groupingBy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;6&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;summarizingDouble&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;treatment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;7&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;8&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;keySet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;forEach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;9&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;10&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;treatment stats: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;11&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;12&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;// making it parallel is as each as this&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;13&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;DoubleSummaryStatistics&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;14&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;         &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatmentStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;parallel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;collect&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;15&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;            &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;groupingBy&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;16&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;              &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Collectors&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;summarizingDouble&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;treatment:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;total&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;17&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;18&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;keySet&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;forEach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;19&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;20&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;treatment stats: &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;summary&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;get&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)));&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-power-of-optional-versus-null&quot;&gt;The power of optional versus null&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t thought fully about the power of optional versus null until listening to the course. Jessica includes an example of how, using optional, we can avoid doing null checks at various levels within our business logic and just handle the empty check at UI level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the example below there might be no instances of treatment which includes wisdom tooth extraction but we don’t need to care about that when retrieving a contractor who has carried it out. If the treatment is empty the map doesn’t get carried out. We only handle it in the UI when we’re displaying our message using orElse to indicate if no matching contractor was found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;code-highlight-figure&quot;&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;code-highlight-caption&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-title&quot;&gt;findExampleOfTreatment.java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;code-highlight-caption-link&quot; href=&quot;https://gist.github.com/5a0e4d916fcf5ccd44ce&quot;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;code-highlight-pre&quot;&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;1&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Optional&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;findExampleOfTreatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatmentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;2&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;treatmentStream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;filter&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;3&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;items&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;anyMatch&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;4&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;      &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;treatmentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;equals&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatmentName&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;))).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;findFirst&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;();&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;5&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;6&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;7&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Optional&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;Contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;findContractorWhoExtractsWisdomTeeth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;()&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;8&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;findExampleOfTreatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Wisdom Tooth Extraction&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;Map&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;9&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;     &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;treatment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;contractor&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;10&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;11&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;12&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;kt&quot;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;main&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;String&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;)&amp;#x7b;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;13&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;System&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;out&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;println&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;Who has experience extracting a Wisdom Tooth? &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;14&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;     &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;+&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;findContractorWhoExtractsWisdomTeeth&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;getFullname&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;().&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;orElse&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;No one!&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;));&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div data-line=&quot;15&quot; class=&quot;code-highlight-row numbered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;code-highlight-line&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;#x7d;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/technologies/functional-programming-with-java/&quot;&gt;Functional Programming with Java&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on October 22, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making Time to Talk]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/making-time-to-talk/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/making-time-to-talk</id>
  <published>2015-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-10-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently finished a project and it made me think about the difference taking time to communicate can make to a person. We are always talking about the importance of not calling people resources. The need to make them feel valued. All too often it is easy to get caught up in dramatic gestures  and forget about the impact of day to day interactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was finishing up on a large project earlier this year, two senior members of the team took time to talk to me 1 to 1. They explained when the project was finishing up and the opportunities beyond this. They were both busy and had a lot of people to look after along with customers to keep happy. That 10-15 mins made me feel more valued than any fancy employee benefits scheme could do. It said I appreciate what you’ve done. I care enough about you and your career to make sure you know the opportunities that lie ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/making-time-to-talk/&quot;&gt;Making Time to Talk&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on October 20, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I'm Bought in to Coaching]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/why-im-bought-in-to-coaching/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/why-im-bought-in-to-coaching</id>
  <published>2015-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-09-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week I was lucky enough to be sent on a two day coaching course led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/bryandunlop&quot;&gt;Bryan Dunlop&lt;/a&gt;. I’d wanted to go on this for a while as I’ve benefited from being coached in the past. I have a number of people who I currently coach but I was looking forward to some formal training to help me maximise the positive impact I could make. It was a brilliant couple of days with lots of practical to get experience applying what we had learnt. Highlights included:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Working out where people were on the skill, will matrix and how to coach for different combinations of skill and will&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Giving effective feedback and the importance of not shying away from difficult conversations but giving constructive feedback to help people tackle areas for improvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GROW_model&quot;&gt;GROW model&lt;/a&gt;. This was brilliant. In the past I’ve struggled with how to structure conversations to help people define their goals and steps to get there. Sometimes it is hard to get people to open up. Now I have a sequence to follow and example questions to draw on I think it’ll help make sessions much more effective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;whats-the-value-in-coaching&quot;&gt;What’s the value in coaching?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are just some of the ways I’ve personally benefited from coaching:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Overcoming self limiting beliefs&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting perspective&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Reinforcing achievements&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding strengths and weaknesses&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Exploring situations I feel I’ve failed at and understanding why so I can learn from it&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping identify what is important. Finding focus&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Realising what was top priority to work on is in fact not the main thing&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Helping find a way of getting from A to B&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Coming up with alternative ways of achieving aim&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Challenging solution to a problem&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Making the unachieveable achieveable&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;finding-a-coach&quot;&gt;Finding a Coach&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience of coaching has not been limited to my formal career coach. I’ve benefited from conversations with colleagues who I respect from a range of roles and backgrounds. It doesn’t have to be someone in the same role or on the same career path or someone with similar personality or experiences. Some of the best coaching I’ve received has been from people who are completely different from me because they challenge my beliefs and natural responses. I’ve been lucky that the people I’ve approached to coach me have been happy to help. If you care about building good relationships with your colleagues day to day you’ll find this is the case. In general we’ve all too much on so make sure you approach the person you want coached by with a purpose and make the most of the time they can spare. Thank them and be appreciative of what they do for you. They don’t have to spend their precious time on you.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/why-im-bought-in-to-coaching/&quot;&gt;Why I'm Bought in to Coaching&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on September 26, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Know How She Does It]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/i-know-how-she-does-it/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/i-know-how-she-does-it</id>
  <published>2015-08-30T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-08-30T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Early on in my pregnancy I was having one of those moments where I wondered how I was going to manage two small people and a career. I’m competitive and want to do well but at the same time my mum gave me and my sister a great childhood staying at home with us so I value spending quality time with my children. I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Know-How-She-Does-Successful/dp/159184732X&quot;&gt;I Know How She Does It&lt;/a&gt; by Laura Vanderkam and I was interested to see how other women carve out their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are loads of interesting tips within the book but some &lt;strong&gt;key&lt;/strong&gt; things which stood out for me were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-dont-fixate-on-the-ideal-be-realistic&quot;&gt;Lesson: Don’t Fixate on the Ideal be Realistic&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be easy to focus on the negative, the times when things go wrong or targets get missed. I’ve fallen into this before both in terms of work and home life. Dismissing a day out because Luke’s played up instead of focusing on the good parts, the special moments spent together. Beating myself up for being tired one night and taking the lazy route in terms of food and entertaining Luke instead of putting it in perspective as a rarity rather than the norm. Getting hung up when someone finds fault in a design instead of focusing on the parts I got right and looking at it as an opportunity to learn. It’s moving away from an obsession with perfectionism to &lt;strong&gt;being realistic, accepting you’re human and giving yourself credit for what you do achieve, actively making an effort to look for the positive.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-zoom-out-from-one-day-and-look-at-the-bigger-picture&quot;&gt;Lesson: Zoom out from one day and look at the bigger picture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For around 6 months I was travelling every other week for 3 days away from home and I felt extremely guilty for doing it and being away from Luke those two nights. Zooming out and looking at the bigger picture it gave me two nights to geek out and have me time. I read books to Luke each night I was away over FaceTime. Keeping up our bedtime routine. I work a 4 day week so was still spending more hours with Luke than many 9-5 five days a week mums. My weekends were freer because of what I’d achieved those two nights I was away. I was refreshed and made more of an effort to appreciate and make the most of my time with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-its-ok-if-9-5-in-the-office-everyday-doesnt-work-for-you&quot;&gt;Lesson: It’s ok if 9-5 in the office everyday doesn’t work for you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found it refreshing to see how many of the women in the book didn’t work typical 9-5 because that totally resonates with me. I work the equivalent of 4 days a week since having Luke. Up until this week that meant working Tuesday to Friday. On a Monday I’d keep an eye on my mail/Skype so I was fairly up on what was happening. It gave me 3 full days with Luke and along with my mum taking him one day meant he spent the majority of the week with family. Now that Luke is starting school I’ve switched to 2 half days and 3 full days so I can pick him up twice a week. If I need to work extra it is rarely carrying on beyond 5, it is generally later at night once I’ve spent time with Luke and put him to bed. Sometimes the OH or my mum picks Luke up and I go hard at it one night so the rest of the week/weekend will not involve overtime. I like to spend the majority of the week in the office as I prefer working with people face to face but working from home the odd day can save me around an hour and a half commuting so it’s great to have the &lt;strong&gt;flex&lt;/strong&gt; to do it at times. Sometimes I work at the weekend or on my day off. If it means I can get something sorted and be present the rest of the time instead of worrying about it then it is worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-make-time-for-what-is-important-to-you&quot;&gt;Lesson: Make time for what is important to you&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The past few months have been my most challenging in terms of finding time for what is important to me. Pregnancy has meant I’m much more tired than usual and my evenings seem to have disappeared. Once Luke is in bed I’m ready for bed. In order to make time for the things that are important I’ve found I need to &lt;strong&gt;plan a bit more and set aside time&lt;/strong&gt;. Normally I exercise at home with Turbofire or run but at the moment I’ve not the motivation to do either so I’ve signed up for two classes, aquabellies and yogabellies. Paying upfront is a motivator to attend and I love it once I’m there. They really help me to chill out and look after myself. In terms of blogging and learning I’m keeping a trello board so if I get spare time I can pick something off the board and get stuck in instead of faffing around trying to decide what to do. I don’t think there is an easy answer when you have small children. I think you have to be creative about fitting things in and accept you will be wrecked at times. It’s worth it. Later in life I’ll get more me time again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-set-yourself-up-to-succeed&quot;&gt;Lesson: Set Yourself up to Succeed&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were lots of things that the women did in the book that I felt would be useful to apply to my own life to help me succeed. As someone who has to leave at a set time to make childcare pickup I liked the idea of performing a &lt;strong&gt;4pm triage&lt;/strong&gt;. Looking at what I have which is outstanding and splitting it in to what has to be done before I leave and what can wait. It’s made me think about how I approach things, making sure I have the ground work in place to get the most out of meetings, conferences etc. Re-evaluating how I’m spending my work time to make sure it is doing something worthwhile. This will be even more important when I return to work after my second child. I want to make sure I &lt;strong&gt;spend my work time wisely and seize opportunities while not overcommitting.&lt;/strong&gt; Easy eh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-be-present&quot;&gt;Lesson: Be Present&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be easy when tired or under pressure to not be truly present in the moment. I think I could definitely be better at this. When I have a big challenge ahead or know I’ve a lot to get through I find it hard to think of anything else. I really want to work at being &lt;strong&gt;focused mentally on what I’m currently doing&lt;/strong&gt;. If I’m having downtime I want to forget what I have on after that. If I’m with Luke I want to be focused on him, enjoying our time together as although I’m currently his best bud I know I won’t always be his number one person to spend time with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-remember-why-you-work&quot;&gt;Lesson: Remember Why you Work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grass is always greener and all that. Sometimes in the haze of working mother guilt I forget why I work. I work for lots of reasons. I enjoy my job and the people I work with. I like the fact that it means I can make an equal contribution to my OH in terms of supporting our family. The money I earn allows me to regularly take Luke places and do things we might not be able to afford on one wage. While some of the reasons are for me others benefit the rest of my family. Again it is keeping perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lesson-plan-some-fun&quot;&gt;Lesson: Plan Some Fun&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book made me re-evaluate my weekday pre and post work time. Every day does not have to be a dinner, bath, bed routine. After work can be a great opportunity to get out and do something with my family. To be fair the Northern Ireland weather hasn’t helped me with this. Normally in the summer Luke and I regularly hit the beach or park after work. I need to be better at thinking of fun indoor things to do. I think I might pull together a bucket list of things to do indoor/outdoor so when we get a day off or some free time I can quickly get an idea of something fun to do instead of wasting time procrastinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Date nights def need to be re-introduced before baby 2 arrives. We’ve been rubbish at this recently mostly because we’ve one parent living near by who already has Luke one day a week. I need to get more creative with the at home date nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;overall&quot;&gt;Overall&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the book gave me some new ideas for how to manage my time, the main thing I took out of it was a sense that how I handle things and feel was totally normal. &lt;strong&gt;Seeing similarities in how other women approached work/child balance was reassuring.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/i-know-how-she-does-it/&quot;&gt;I Know How She Does It&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on August 30, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just Trying Not To Lean Out]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/life/just-trying-not-to-lean-out/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/life/just-trying-not-to-lean-out</id>
  <published>2015-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2015-07-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Long time no post. Over the past few months I’ve been getting to grips with being pregnant again. Turns out a girl can forget what it is like when you leave a 4 year gap between children. I can’t complain as I have had it pretty easy both times. Still there are definitely differences this time. With a four year old running about chances to rest up are hard to find. Luke combined with a role with more responsibility have left me feeling pretty tired and this time I didn’t escape the dreaded morning sickness. Now I’m in my second trimester I can feel my energy coming back and the thought of travel doesn’t fill me with dread (as it did when I was trying to not succumb to sickness)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This second baby is very much wanted. To be honest it is long overdue as after Luke I put things on hold so I could have a bit of career time. Coming back from maternity leave is not the easiest. A year out of the office (my choice I know and one I’m lucky to have) can leave you feeling a bit shaky in confidence and it definitely took me a bit of time (and complaining) to make people realise I didn’t want to coast. Once I did I got on to some really interesting projects and I’ve had a ball. Having a second baby is definitely not an excuse to escape work (if you’ve ever tried being home 24x7 with a child you’ll know this is a pretty bad plan as there are literally no breaks. You can’t pee alone and chances of drinking your coffee while hot are slim) but I didn’t want to leave any bigger a gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve definitely had to make some adjustments to my expectations of what I can achieve over the past few months. I’ve fought the tiredness but reality is I haven’t been able to dedicate as much time outside of work to things as I’d like. I’ve a pretty extensive list of books, podcasts and courses that I haven’t got round to completing and as shown by the gap in posts the blogging has gone a bit out the window (lots of ideas but not the matching energy/motivation to write). I’ve had to cut myself some slack and accept that I can’t do quite as much as I normally would and I’ve skipped on a few opportunities I normally wouldn’t. (I make this sound like I accepted this easily. No chance I’ve been pretty humped about it and resisted giving in) I’ve tried not to lean out i.e. I’m still giving my all to the essentials like my day to day job and coaching but I’m just not volunteering for as much extra stuff as usual. It’s not that I care less about my job or have lowered my expectations its just the reality is my body is busy making a baby and that takes it out of you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thought of being on maternity leave is amazing and scary. I can’t wait to spend quality time with baby Campbell 2 ( or Yoghurt Baby Campbell as Luke has named him… best not to leave name choices to 4 year olds I think) Plus it is Luke’s first year at school so I’m glad to be able to devote time to getting him settled and helping him adjust. I learnt a few lessons from my first return from maternity leave and I’m trying to put the ground work in to ensure a smoothish return. I’ve spoken with my coach about my concerns and we’ve agreed to come up with a training plan to get me back up to speed. I’ve made clear my desire to continue enjoying my career and taking on challenging roles. I probably shouldn’t even be thinking about it now or during maternity leave but I really felt like everything stalled last time and I can still remember how frustrating that was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was off on maternity leave last time I took the time to upskill in a number of things including Scala and Ruby. Nightly feeds were often to a tech podcast. (What else is there to do at 2 in the morning) There are already a million things I want to learn on my maternity leave like finally getting to devote some time to Clojure (just because I want to, functional programming appeals to the mathematician in me) obviously I’m blanking out the lack of sleep and attention a new born requires. Something makes me think I’ll have to reset my expectations again in a few months time.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/life/just-trying-not-to-lean-out/&quot;&gt;Just Trying Not To Lean Out&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on July 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Does Everyone Know They're Empowered?]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/does-everyone-know-theyre-empowered/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/does-everyone-know-theyre-empowered</id>
  <published>2015-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-03-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve just finishing reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Decision-Maker-Dennis-Bakke/dp/0983263329&quot;&gt;The Decision Maker&lt;/a&gt; based on a recommendation in Kate Matsudaira’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://popforms.com/what-to-read-in-2015/&quot;&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Highly recommend it as a means of helping anyone understand the benefits of empowerment and the stumbling blocks you’ll experience along the way. Being fiction it is easy to read and remember the message it delivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking about the smells that indicate we’re not doing all the right things to make our new way of working stick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a look in terms of empowering people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;were-empowered-no-one-told-me&quot;&gt;We’re Empowered? No one told me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first mistake can be in assuming everyone knows about it. We need to &lt;strong&gt;explicitly make people aware they’re empowered&lt;/strong&gt;. Doing this as a one time policy launch is not sufficient. New people join and people forget. Our values and culture need to be part of the induction programme, they need to be visible in one accesible, location where people can go and see them. They need to be explained in a &lt;strong&gt;simple, succinct way&lt;/strong&gt; so people take time to listen and understand what it means for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;empowerment-thats-just-a-way-of-making-more-money-for-the-company&quot;&gt;Empowerment that’s just a way of making more money for the company&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowerment might seem like a no brainer to us, bringing benefits to the company &lt;strong&gt;and its people&lt;/strong&gt; but if it is not communicated properly and sincerely people could be skeptical. It might be clear to us that empowerment is good for employees in terms of job satisfication, growth and assuming responsibility. Just because we know that doesn’t mean everyone else does. The value needs to be made explicit rather than assuming everyone gets it. People need to know &lt;strong&gt;why the company is doing it and what it means for them&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;empowerment-allows-people-with-no-leadership-experience-to-make-decisions-how-can-that-be-good&quot;&gt;Empowerment allows people with no leadership experience to make decisions. How can that be good?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone will not automatically buy into a decision. To assume they will is naive and to give up on them because they don’t instantly get it can be a waste of talent. Imagine if you’ve worked hard to get to the point where you are leading a team and suddenly you’re told to let your team make some of the decisions you’ve been making. You might feel afraid of losing power or wonder what you’re role is. For a newly graduated employee you might feel you’re not ready to make decisions, unsure if you have the knowledge and experience. Do you think the first can’t be a team lead anymore or the second has no drive and is a waste of effort? No, at least not initially. Change is scary especially if you’ve been comfortable with the state of things before the change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to &lt;strong&gt;recognise the blockers&lt;/strong&gt; to people getting on board and &lt;strong&gt;address them&lt;/strong&gt; by helping coach them past what is holding them back. Some people may never get onboard and in that case it may be time for them to move on. For many showing you care enough to take time to understand and work through their concerns will be enough to make them change and convince them of the sincerity behind the change&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-dont-see-anyone-else-doing-it&quot;&gt;I don’t see anyone else doing it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of empowering people needs to be more than a sentence somewhere. It must be &lt;strong&gt;visible in the day to day life&lt;/strong&gt; of the company. Examples of it need to be made visible to others to help spark ideas of their own. People need to see those who seize being empowered and make positive changes rewarded. Seeing the benefits it brings to others will inspire them to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;great-im-empowered-but-how-do-i-make-a-good-decision&quot;&gt;Great I’m empowered but how do I make a good decision?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want people to innovate and make decisions that bring value to the company. Giving advice on how to go about making a good decision does not hinder it as long as it is &lt;strong&gt;light weight&lt;/strong&gt;. Encouraging people to sound ideas off others, seek advice from people with different specialities and being explicit about how to get budget and equipment encourage good decision making and do not stiffle creativity. &lt;strong&gt;Guidance&lt;/strong&gt; can be useful in reassuring people they are making the &lt;strong&gt;right move&lt;/strong&gt; and make them &lt;strong&gt;aware of the resources in place&lt;/strong&gt; to help them. People need to know who to go to if they have queries round how to go about it.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/culture/does-everyone-know-theyre-empowered/&quot;&gt;Does Everyone Know They're Empowered?&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on March 28, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Commitment]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-commitment/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-commitment</id>
  <published>2015-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2015-02-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Over the past day I’ve been reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Commitment-Novel-about-Managing-Project/dp/9082056909&quot;&gt;Commitment&lt;/a&gt; by Olav Maassen, Chris Matts and Chris Geary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Commitment is a graphic novel which makes it easily devoured and once I started I couldn’t put it down until it was read. After a long day at work an easy read is welcome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the takeaways from commitment:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Don’t treat options as commitments&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you’re unsure of the correct approach you have 3 choices. Postpone the decision and collect more info. Choose the option easiest to change. Invest in an approach which allows change to be easier.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value clearing technical debt&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value making your work and its flow through the stages visual&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multitasking creates hidden queues. See one thing through to completion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Focus on end result. Prioritise what brings value and then identify steps to deliver&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Value staff liquidity. No keyman. Allocate people with least options first and most options last. Don’t need 100% liquidity, more like 10%&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Opposite of a good relationship is no relationship&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-commitment/&quot;&gt;Review: Commitment&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on February 24, 2015.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Attitude]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/attitude/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/attitude</id>
  <published>2014-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2014-12-31T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With just hours left before 2015 a final post driven by the events of the past week. Over the Christmas hols I’ve experienced going from the best feeling in the world to one of the saddest points in my life and it got me thinking about the power of having the right attitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes in life things happen, horrible things and often whether they happen or not is something you have no control over. This was the case in the past few days. There was nothing I could have done to prevent what happened taking place. What I did have control over is how I reacted. The old me would have spent weeks feeling down, wondering why her and generally getting sucked down by it. A victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I refuse to be that person and so while I have shed a tear or two and wondered briefly why me, I’m now dusting myself off and looking forward to new opportunities in 2015. Reflecting on the event, learning lessons and making changes. Trying to get something positive out of it. It is not the end just a set back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve learnt over the past year or two the benefit of taking a positive attitude, embracing failure and criticism, seeing it as an opportunity to grow and a motivation to change, prove it wrong and succeed.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/development/attitude/&quot;&gt;Attitude&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on December 31, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[If Something's Important Make it Visible]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/agile/if-somethings-important-make-it-visible/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/agile/if-somethings-important-make-it-visible</id>
  <published>2014-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2014-11-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the things I’ve learnt over the past year is the power of making things &lt;strong&gt;visible&lt;/strong&gt; to people. Get it up on the wall where it can’t be ignored. That way everyday the team is reminded of it and when it is staring you in the face you tend to take action on it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great candidates are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things you want to improve&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rules which should be followed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Targets you want to hit&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Things the whole team needs to be aware of&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;System Diagrams&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Screen Flows&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;examples&quot;&gt;Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some examples but the possibilities are endless&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encouraging-regular-knowledge-sharing&quot;&gt;Encouraging Regular Knowledge Sharing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Knowledge sharing getting neglected because of other work? Single points of failure due to siloing of expertise? Lack of attendance of Whitebags?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get up on the wall when the last one took place and the number of people who attended. Making people aware that a large amount of time has passed since the last session or that attendance was poor helps provoke conversation and action to improve. Better still have a place on the wall for suggestions for whitebags, scheduling for future sessions and volunteers to run one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/images/visibility/Whitebag.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Whitebag Statistics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encouraging-good-quality-code-reviews&quot;&gt;Encouraging Good Quality Code Reviews&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want to encourage consistency in the quality of code reviews across your team?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a team pull together a list of things to check for and display the list on the wall. Don’t stick it in some wiki or fileshare where it will get lost. Now there is no excuse for a sloppy review&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/images/visibility/CheckList.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Codereview Checklist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encouraging-timely-code-reviews&quot;&gt;Encouraging Timely Code Reviews&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stories taking ages to progress to test because code reviews are not getting done?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Create a board with peoples’ names and place the story card for the piece of work against the name of the reviewer. Once they’ve completed it they can move it back to the developer or progress it to test depending on the outcome. A code review which hasn’t been progressed is much more visible here than in a code review tracking tool. Better still agree a period in which it has to be carried out and add it to the board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/images/visibility/CodeReview.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Codereview Tracking Board&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;encouraging-timely-resolving-of-bugs&quot;&gt;Encouraging Timely Resolving of Bugs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stories stuck in test because of unresolved bugs?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the blocked story add a post-it for each defect with the id of the defect. Now you have an instant understanding of how many bugs are sitting against a story. It promotes conversation on priority of bug resolving vs other work. It helps identify stories which have been stuck over a number of days and highlights issues in quality of code, story definition or the code review process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/images/visibility/TestBoard.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;Stories Blocked in Test&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is just a small selection of the things my team has made visible. Hope it helps spark some ideas for things to display in your project&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/agile/if-somethings-important-make-it-visible/&quot;&gt;If Something's Important Make it Visible&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on November 28, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sound Learning Advice]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/sound-learning-advice/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/sound-learning-advice</id>
  <published>2014-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
  <updated>2014-11-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With so much interesting stuff happening in technology it can be hard to know where to start when trying to keep up to date. It can overwhelm you to the point where you don’t start. If you’re looking for some sound advice check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/trisha_gee&quot;&gt;Trisha Gee&lt;/a&gt;’s post on &lt;a href=&quot;http://trishagee.github.io/post/staying_ahead_of_the_curve/&quot;&gt;Staying ahead of the curve&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two things I liked in particular:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;She emphasizes the importance of deciding to not learn something. Take time to rule out things.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Just because you decide to not learn something now doesn’t mean you can never pick it up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/learning/sound-learning-advice/&quot;&gt;Sound Learning Advice&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on November 26, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Talking with Tech Leads]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-talking-with-tech-leads/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-talking-with-tech-leads</id>
  <published>2014-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-24T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A couple of weeks ago I was having a browse around the books on &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com&quot;&gt;Leanpub&lt;/a&gt; and I came across &lt;a href=&quot;https://leanpub.com/talking-with-tech-leads&quot;&gt;Talking with Tech Leads&lt;/a&gt; by Patrick Kua. The book contains 35 interviews with Tech Leads from first timers to experienced pros. It looks at how they balance the technical and non technical demands. The interviews illustrate how the reality of being a tech lead differs from their expectations. The tech leads talk about the skills they’ve had to develop along the way and the lessons they’ve learnt. It is an easy read due to the interview format. I would recommend it to senior developers looking to make the transition as it is an insight into what a day being a tech lead involves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over my next couple of posts I’m going to explore some of the topics in the book which resonated with me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redefining Your Value&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Building Up Others&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Welcoming Input&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeing the Bigger Picture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Staying in Touch with the Code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Developing Yourself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Valuing Building Relationships&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Establishing Team Culture&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Managing Your Time&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Disagreement is Not Criticism&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-talking-with-tech-leads/&quot;&gt;Review: Talking with Tech Leads&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on October 24, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Show Your Work!]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-show-your-work/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-show-your-work</id>
  <published>2014-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-10-12T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found &lt;a href=&quot;http://austinkleon.com/show-your-work/&quot;&gt;Show Your Work!&lt;/a&gt; by Austin Kleon an inspiration for getting out there and sharing what you know and do. It’s an easy to read and digest book, split into 10 chapters, each packed with beautiful illustrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book reassures that you don’t need to be an expert to have something worth sharing. Through its pages it gives simple steps to follow to get your thoughts out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was looking for insights for my blog and speaking. The book provided this. It made me look closer at my day to day working and inspirations. I hadn’t stepped back and thought about my inspirations before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapters on how to share were also useful. I need to follow Kleon’s advice and start sharing little more often. In my job it is easy to overlook the small things which go into delivering a successful project. Taking time out to share these is a good way of making myself more aware of what I’m doing well. It’s good to appreciate the little wins. It is also good to recognise them for future projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book promotes taking time to pick the prose to share your thoughts as you would if writing a story. It also warns against spamming. I liked the idea of self editing, not sharing for the sake of sharing, make it useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was glad to see a section on teaching what you know as I’m a huge believer in doing that and the benefits it brings you. It takes you understanding to a new level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the past I have held back sharing my opinion in writing or when speaking because of fear. Fear of being cut down either by trolls or people who know more than me. Kleon offers sound advice on this, making you take a look at why you feel this way. Not easy but worth confronting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spend a lot of time reading technical books and this is a welcome distraction from those. It gave me a reassuring push that I’m doing the right thing sharing my thoughts. That a lone made it worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/books/review-show-your-work/&quot;&gt;Review: Show Your Work!&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on October 12, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Little Book of Lunch]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/the-little-book-of-lunch/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/the-little-book-of-lunch</id>
  <published>2014-09-08T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-09-08T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I thought it would be good to start sharing things that help me to be a happy, healthy programmer. This post falls under that category and is a review of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Little-Book-Lunch-Caroline-Craig/dp/0224095730/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1410190693&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+little+book+of+lunch&quot;&gt;The Little Book of Lunch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tend to mostly take a packed lunch to work and had got stuck in a real sandwich and soup rut. I’m pretty flat out at the moment and lunchtime is my little sanctuary of calm and it just felt like I wasn’t making the most of it. I wanted to change up my lunch and start making it something I really looked forward to. Something that would lift my spirits and leave be feeling revitalised after a hard morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wandering through a bookshop one lunchtime I came across &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Little-Book-Lunch-Caroline-Craig/dp/0224095730/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1410190693&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+little+book+of+lunch&quot;&gt;The Little Book of Lunch&lt;/a&gt;. Flicking through the pages I was impressed by how many of the recipes appealed to me. In general the recipes require a small number of ingredients. I don’t want to have to buy in a million things for one lunch. They also tend to have a short preparation time. Having a fulltime job, house, toddler and dog to look after means spare time is at a premium. The book even simplifies your weekly shop by grouping recipes with similar ingredients and providing a shopping list. Genius.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve had the book a couple of months now and I’ve not been disappointed in a recipe yet. I’ve tried lots of different things including:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Herby Quinoa With Peas &amp;amp; Seasonal Greens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Spanish Lunch: Chorizo Egg &amp;amp; Potato Salad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rainbow Rescue&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Vietnamese Salad&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;South-East Asian Pho&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thai Fishcakes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Harissa Chicken&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Simple Tortilla&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Salted Caramel Brownies (I don’t want to count how many of the batch I ate myself. Scared to make the peanut butter ones as I’d prob eat the lot)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lemon Curd Cupcakes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve enjoyed them all and they’ve transported well too. I feel like I’m fuelling my body with something healthy and not processed and they feel like a treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help with transporting I got myself some really cute Tupperware from Paperchase a bit like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paperchase.co.uk/gifts/home-and-kitchen-gifts/lunch-boxes-bottles/all-change-snack-boxes-set-of-4.html&quot;&gt;these&lt;/a&gt;. (If my 20 year old self could see me now she’d be so disappointed at me getting excited about this). The smallest one is great for dressings. Also got myself a wee flask from ikea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found I’m using herbs so much more that I’m now growing mint, coriander and basil. Sainsburys sell them at a pound a pop so very small outlay and so far they’ve survived and I’m by no means the most green fingered of people. Breaking off a mint stalk, sticking it in a cup and adding boiled water makes the best mint tea. Much better than a teabag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re looking to spruce up your lunchtimes look no further than &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Little-Book-Lunch-Caroline-Craig/dp/0224095730/ref=sr_1_1?s=books&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1410190693&amp;amp;sr=1-1&amp;amp;keywords=the+little+book+of+lunch&quot;&gt;The Little Book of Lunch&lt;/a&gt;. Well worth a purchase.&lt;/p&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/the-little-book-of-lunch/&quot;&gt;The Little Book of Lunch&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on September 08, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Scenius]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/scenius/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/scenius</id>
  <published>2014-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first chapter in Austin Kleon’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://austinkleon.com/show-your-work/&quot;&gt;Show Your Work!&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to a brilliant word “Scenius” which he credited muscian Brian Eno with creating. It’s the argument that no great genius existed in a vacuum. Instead they were part of a scene. Interacting with other people, sharing ideas, building on what others had come up with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While we all can’t be geniuses we can benefit from being part of a scene. As a developer I can learn things on my own, build things on my own and never share what I’ve learnt, the processes I’ve used or the things that I’ve built. That would get me so far but what gets me much further is opening up so people can see what I’ve done. OK that leaves me exposed to scary critique or risking looking like a novice but if I’m willing to take these risks I get the benefit of feedback and other peoples’ different take on things. Everyone has their own experiences and influences that mean they look at things differently. Interacting can help me see new ways of doing things, new places to take my applications/learning and introduce me to new influences that broaden my outlook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love being part of both physical and virtual scenes. Attending meetups and workshops and sharing my ideas over twitter and this blog. I can see the benefits both in terms of my work and my attitude to life. Being part of a scene has driven me to learn more about my trade, overcome my fear of speaking in front of a group and being wrong and increased my joy for learning and trying new things. Seeing what others have achieved and their passion is inspiring and infectious. If you aren’t already part of a scene go out and find a meetup where you can talk about the things you do. If there isn’t one near you find one online or start one up.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/scenius/&quot;&gt;Scenius&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on August 10, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Invention Machine]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/invention-machine/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/invention-machine</id>
  <published>2014-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-08-10T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Don’t think of your website as a self-promotion machine, instead think of it as a self-invention machine. Fill your website with your work and your ideas and the stuff you care about. Austin Kleon, Show Your Work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently in the process of reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://austinkleon.com/show-your-work/&quot;&gt;Show Your Work!&lt;/a&gt; (which is great) and I really loved this quote. I started this site up a couple of years ago when returning to work after having Luke mainly as a means of making myself accountable to keep learning and sharing what I learned. On reading the quote it made me re-evaluate what I was posting so you’ll probably notice me posting some stuff that is less specific to IT but I feel helps me be a happier more productive programmer. I’ll also be posting some shorter posts on things which have inspired or struck a cord with me. I guess on the whole I want the site to have a bit more personality and represent better who I am.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/invention-machine/&quot;&gt;Invention Machine&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on August 10, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Driving Technical Change]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-driving-technical-change/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-driving-technical-change</id>
  <published>2014-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-06-17T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I always enjoy books published by the Pragmatic Programmers and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.co.uk/Driving-Technical-Change-Terrence-Ryan/dp/1934356603&quot;&gt;Driving Technical Change&lt;/a&gt; by Terrence Ryan was no exception. The premise of the book is that people don’t always adopt good ideas simply because they are a good idea instead we need to put some thought into how to sell the idea in order to increase the chance of it being adopted. People need to feel the investment of their time/effort/money is going to reap reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book is split into two sections. The first section helps you identify the types of sceptics who you will need to win over. These include the uninformed, the herd, the cynic, the burned, the timecrunched, the boss and the irrational (who are a lost cause). Some might complain that people don’t fit neatly into boxes but I think that misses the point which is it makes you stop and really think about the people on your team. What is their personality? Do they have a glass half full or empty mentality? What is their experience? Are they a nine to fiver or someone who IT is more than a job? Beyond driving change, the scope of this book, it is a useful exercise to try to understand others views and feelings and be sympathetic to them. I think it helps you find a way to get the most out of people and shows a level of respect for them. Each type of sceptic is examined with an explanation of why they behave this way. I particularly like the way Ryan emphasised for the burned that a change doesn’t have to have gone wrong, a change which brings no benefit also leads to a negative view of change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve identified the types of sceptics you need to persuade the second half of the book shows you the different techniques you can use to build traction for your idea. The techniques are nothing new for a seasoned developer but it is a good reminder and the book goes further showing you which technique will help you most with each type of sceptic. Techniques covered include gaining expertise, delivering your message, demonstrating your technique, creating trust, proposing compromise, getting publicity (externally e.g. open sourcing your code), focusing on synergy (are there other industry specific concerns the tool can help address like security, waste, environmentalism), building a bridge (interim step(s) to adoption) and creating something compelling (sample project).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book does a good job of making you examine your motives when pushing a technical change to make sure it is for the right reasons and that you’ve looked for and thought about alternate approaches. Don’t just be a fanboy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The book wraps up with helping you come up with a strategy, identifying who to target first, who to not waste energy on and how to use the converted to gain momentum to get others on board. Finally Ryan covers convincing management by solving their problems. This involves speaking in business terms rather than technical gains e.g. reducing ongoing project costs instead of more maintainable code and giving meaningful figures such as man days saved etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the book is a good read, reminding you of the need to recognise your team as individuals who will react differently. It makes you aware of the range of tools you have to help get a technical change adopted (which are also beneficial for building your profile) and it hits home the fact that &lt;strong&gt;business drives business&lt;/strong&gt;. The people who hold the power care about making choices that bring business benefit and you need to care too.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/review-driving-technical-change/&quot;&gt;Review: Driving Technical Change&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on June 17, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Roundup May 27th 2014]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://heatherjcampbell.com/weekly-roundup-3/"/>
  <id>http://heatherjcampbell.com/weekly-roundup-3</id>
  <published>2014-05-27T00:00:00+01:00</published>
  <updated>2014-05-27T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Heather Campbell</name>
    <uri>http://heatherjcampbell.com</uri>
    <email>heatherjcampbell@hotmail.co.uk</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-have-i-been-reading&quot;&gt;What Have I Been Reading&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;pastry-box-project&quot;&gt;Pastry Box Project&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://the-pastry-box-project.net/&quot;&gt;Pastry Box Project&lt;/a&gt; provides a thought a day from 30 people who are influential in their field. Lot of interesting and varied thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ivana-mcconnell&quot;&gt;Ivana McConnell&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re thinking about getting involved in helping people learn technology but need a bit of a push take a read at &lt;a href=&quot;https://the-pastry-box-project.net/baker/ivana-mcconnell&quot;&gt;Ivana McConnell’s article&lt;/a&gt;. She explains the benefits in ignoring imposter syndrome and going for it. Not only will the pupils benefit but I can guarantee you’ll understand the subject matter and how to teach it better. I know how much I got out of giving an ‘Introduction to Ruby’ at the WWC. You only think you know a topic until you try to teach it to someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whitney-hess-who-do-we-think-we-are&quot;&gt;Whitney Hess: Who do We Think We Are?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href=&quot;https://the-pastry-box-project.net/whitney-hess/2014-april-10&quot;&gt;Who do We Think We Are?&lt;/a&gt; Whitney Hess looks at why we find the need to look for the negative in people. It’s something that really resonated with me. I struggle at times with the trolling which goes on via twitter and the internet in general. I’m not expecting everyone to agree but I don’t believe there is the need to tear someone apart just because they hold a different point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;manning&quot;&gt;Manning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.manning.com/fogus2/&quot;&gt;Joy of Clojure 2nd Edition&lt;/a&gt; has just become available to purchase in print. I got the chance to review this and it was an addictive read. if you don’t already appreciate the beauty of Clojure you will by the end of reading this book. It goes beyond teaching Clojure syntax to explaining the concepts behind it and demonstrating how to write beautiful code. It really is a joy to read. I’m looking forwards to going back to it over the summer and being able to enjoy it without the pressure of a deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outlier-developer&quot;&gt;Outlier Developer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cory House’s Outlier Developer site regularly features guest posts and the one this week really caught my eye. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.outlierdeveloper.com/the-road-from-nobody-to-half-a-somebody/&quot;&gt;The road from nobody to half a somebody&lt;/a&gt; is packed full of great advice about getting started with blogging. Kevin O’Shaughnessy’s article pulls together lots of resources which are worth a read. I really need to follow his advice and start getting into a proper schedule. I’m still a bit hit and miss about posting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-have-i-been-doing&quot;&gt;What Have I Been Doing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reviewing&quot;&gt;Reviewing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve gotten involved in reviewing an early draft of another book for Manning. If you’re interesting in getting involved click &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.manning.com/about/reviewer.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I can highly recommend it. Not only do you get the great feeling of helping to improve a book but you’ll also improve your technical skills. Plus there is nothing like a deadline for making time for a bit of reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presenting&quot;&gt;Presenting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I presented internally on Java 8. I’ll get the slides and a blog post up later this week. I really enjoy the functional style of programming as it can be used to create clean and easy to read code. I’ll go into greater depth in my post.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com/weekly-roundup-3/&quot;&gt;Weekly Roundup May 27th 2014&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Heather Campbell at &lt;a href=&quot;http://heatherjcampbell.com&quot;&gt;Technical Musing of a Mummy&lt;/a&gt; on May 27, 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>
